2 as As they entered they saw Dorian Gray. He was seated at the piano, with his
back to them, turning over the pages of a volume of schuman's Forest
Scenes.” “You must lend me these, Basil,” he cried. “I want to learn them. They are
perfectly charming.” “That entirely depends on how you sit today Dorian.” “Oh, I am
tired of sitting, and I don’t want a life-size portrait of myself,” answered
the lad, swinging around on the music stool in a willful petulant manner. When
he caught sight of Lord Henry, a faint blush colored his cheeks for a moment,
and he started up. “I beg your pardon, Basil, but I didn’t know you had anyone
with you.” “This is Lord Henry Waton Dorian, an old Oxford friend of mine I've just
been telling him what a capital sitter you were, and now you have spoiled
everything.” “You have not spoiled my pleasure in meeting you, Mr. Gray,” said
Lord Henry, stepping forward and extending his hand. “My aunt has often
spoken to me about you. You are one of her favorites and I'm afraid, one of her
victims also I'm in Lady Agatha’s black books at present,” answered Dorian with a funny look of
penitence. “I promised to go to a club in White Chapel with her last Tuesday, and I
really forgot all about it. We were to have played a duet together— —three duets,
I believe. I don’t know what she will say
to me. I am far too frightened to call.” “Oh,
I will make your peace with my arm a She
is quite devoted to you. And I don’t think it really matters about your not
being there. The audience probably thought it was a duet. When Aunt Agatha
sits down to the piano, she makes quite enough noise for two people.” “That is very
horrid to her, and not very nice to me,” answered Dorian, laughing. Lord Henry looked at
him. Yes, he was certainly wonderfully handsome, with his finely curved scarlet
lips, his frank blue eyes, his crisp gold hair. There was something in his face
that made one trust him at once. All the cander of youth was there, as well as all
youth’s passionate purity. One felt that he had kept himself unspotted from the
world. No wonder Basil hallwood worshiped him. “You are too charming to go in for
philanthropy, Mr. Gray— —far too charming.” And Lord Henry flung himself down on the
divan and opened his cigarette case The painter had been busy mixing his
colors and getting his brushes ready. He was looking worried, and when he heard
Lord Henry’s last remark, he glanced at him, hesitated for a moment, and then said,
“Harry, I want to finish this picture today Would you think it awfully rude of
me if I asked you to go away?” Lord Henry smiled and looked at
Dorian Gray. “Am I to go, Mr. Gray?” he asked. “Oh, please don’t, Lord Henry. I see
that Basil is in one of his sulky moods, and I can’t bear him when he sulks.
Besides, I want you to tell me why I should not go in for
philanthropy.” “I don’t know that I shall tell you that, Mr. Gray. It is so tedious a
subject that one would have to talk seriously about it. But I certainly shall
not run away, now that you have asked me to stop. You don’t really mind, Basil, do
you youve often told me that you lik your sitters to have someone to chat to
hallwood bit his lip. “If Dorian wishes it, of course you must stay. Dorian’s whims
are laws to everybody, except himself.” Lord Henry took up his hat and gloves.
“You are very pressing, Basil, but I'm afraid I must go. I promised to meet a
man at the oon Goodbye Mr. Gray. Come and see me some afternoon in Ken Street I'm nearly
always at home at 5:00 Write to me when
you are coming. I should be sorry to miss you bad cried Dorian Gray, “if Lord Henry Waton
goes, I shall go, too. You never open your lips while you are painting, and it is
horribly dull standing on a platform and trying to look pleasant. Ask him to stay.
I insist upon it.” “Stay, Harry, to oblige Dorian, and to oblige me,” said hallwood
gazing intently at his picture. “It is quite true, I never talk
when I'm working, and never listen either, and it must be dreadfully tedious for my unfortunate
sitters. I beg you to stay.” “But what about my man at the oons The painter laughed. “I
don’t think there will be any difficulty about that. Sit down again, Harry. And now,
Dorian, get up on the platform, and don’t move about too much, or pay any attention
to what Lord Henry says. He has a very bad influence over all his friends, with
the single exception of myself.” Dorian Gray stepped up on the
deis with the air of a young Greek martyr, and made a little moo of
discontent to Lord Henry, to whom he had rather taken a fancy. He was so unlike
Basil. They made a delightful contrast. And he had such a beautiful
voice. After a few moments he said to him, “Have you really a very bad influence,
Lord Henry? As bad as Basil says?” “There is no such thing as a good influence, Mr.
Gray. All influence is immoral— —immoral from the scientific point of view.”
“Why?” “Because to influence a person is to give him one’s own soul. He does not
think his natural thoughts, or burn with his natural passions. His virtues are not
real to him. His sins, if there are such things as sins, are borrowed. He becomes
an echo of someone else’s music, an actor of a part that has not been written for
him. The aim of life is self-development.
To realize one’s nature perfectly— —that is what each of us is here for. People
are afraid of themselves, nowadays. They have forgotten the highest of all duties,
the duty that one owes to oneself Of course, they are charitable. They feed the
hungry and clothe the beggar. But their own souls starve, and are
naked. Courage has gone out of our race.
Perhaps we never really had it. The terror of society, which is the basis of
morals, the terror of God, which is the secret of religion— —these are the two
things that govern us. And yet or Just turn your head a little more
to the right, Dorian, like a good boy,” said the painter, deep in his work and
conscious only that a look had come into the lad’s face that he had never seen there
before. “And yet,” continued Lord Henry, in his low, musical voice, and with that
graceful wave of the hand that was always so characteristic of him, and that
he had even in his eaten days, “I believe that if one man were to live out his
life fully and completely, were to give form to every feeling, expression to
every thought, reality to every dream— —I believe that the world would gain such a
fresh impulse of joy that we would forget all the maladies of medievalism
and return to the helenic ideal— —to something finer, richer than the helenic ideal, it may be.
But the bravest man amongst us is afraid of himself. The mutilation of the savage
has its tragic survival in the self-denial that mars our
lives. We are punished for our refusals.
Every impulse that we strive to strangle broods in the mind and poisons us. The
body sins once, and has done with its sin, for action is a mode of
purification. Nothing remains then but the recollection of a pleasure, or the
luxury of a regret.
The only way to get rid of a temptation is to yield to it. Resist it, and your
soul grows sick with longing for the things it has forbidden to itself, with
desire for what its monstrous laws have made monstrous and
unlawful. It has been said that the great events of the world take place in the
brain. It is in the brain, and the brain only, that the great sins of the world
take place also. You, Mr. Gray, you yourself, with your rose red youth
and your rose white boyhood, you have had passions that have made you afraid,
thoughts that have filled you with terror Daydreams and sleeping dreams
whose mere memory might stain your cheek with shame—” “Stop!” faltered Dorian Gray, “stop! you
bewilder me. I don’t know what to say.
There is some answer to you, but I cannot find it. Don’t speak. Let me think. Or,
rather, let me try not to think.” For nearly 10 minutes he stood there,
motionless, with parted lips and eyes strangely bright. He was dimly conscious that
entirely fresh influences were at work within him. Yet they seemed to him to
have come really from himself. The few words that Basil’s
friend had said to him— —words spoken by chance, no doubt, and with willful paradox
in them— —had touched some secret cord that had never been touched before, but
that he felt was now vibrating and throbbing to curious pulses. Music had
stirred him like that. Music had troubled him many times. But music was not
articulate. It was not a new world, but rather another chaos, that it created in
us. Words! Mere words! How terrible they were! How clear, and vivid, and cruel! One
could not escape from them. And yet what a subtle magic there was in them! They
seem to be able to give a plastic form to formless things, and to have a music
of their own as sweet as that of vile or of loot Mere words! Was there anything so
real as words? Yes; there had been things in his boyhood that he had not understood. He
understood them now. Life suddenly became fiery colored to him. It seemed to him
that he had been walking in fire. Why had he not known it? With his subtle smile,
Lord Henry watched him. He knew the precise psychological moment went to say
nothing. He felt intensely interested. He was amazed at the sudden
impression that his words had produced, and, remembering a book that he had read
when he was 16 a book which had revealed to him much that he had not known before,
he wondered whether Dorian Gray was passing through a similar
experience. He had merely shot an arrow into the air. Had it hit the mark? How
fascinating the lad was hallwood painted away with that marvelous bold touch of
his, that had the true refinement and perfect delicacy that in art, at any rate
comes only from strength. He was unconscious of the silence. “Basil I'm tired of standing,”
cried Dorian graay suddenly. “I must go out and sit in the garden. The air is
stifling here.” “My dear fellow, I am so sorry. When I'm painting, I can’t think of
anything else. But you never sat better.
You were perfectly still. And I have caught the effect I wanted— —the half-
parted lips and the bright look in the eyes. I don’t know what Harry has been
saying to you, but he has certainly made you have the most wonderful expression. I
suppose he's been paying you compliments.
You mustn’t believe a word that he says.” “He has certainly not been paying me
compliments. Perhaps that is the reason that I don’t believe anything he has
told me.” “You know you believe it all,” said Lord Henry, looking at him with his
dreamy langor eyes. “I will go out to the garden with you. It is horribly hot in
the studio. Basil, let us have something ice to drink, something with strawberries in
it.” “Certainly, Harry. Just touch the bell, and when Parker comes I will tell him
what you want I've got to work up this background, so I will join you later on.
Don’t keep Dorian too long I've never been in better form for painting than I am today
This is going to be my masterpiece. It is my masterpiece as it
stands.” Lord Henry went out to the garden and found Dorian Gray burying his face
in the great cool lilac blossoms feverishly drinking in their perfume as if it had been
wine. He came close to him and put his hand upon his
shoulder. “You are quite right to do that,” he murmured. “Nothing can cure the soul but
the senses, just as nothing can cure the senses but the soul.”
The lad started and drew back. He was bareheaded, and the leaves had tossed his
rebellious curls and tangled all their gilded threads. There was a look of fear in his
eyes, such as people have when they are suddenly awakened. His finely chiseled nostrils
quivered, and some hidden nerve shook the scarlet of his lips and left them
[Music]
trembling. “Yes,” continued Lord Henry, “that is one of the great secrets of life— —to
cure the soul by means of the senses, and the senses by means of the soul. You are
a wonderful creation. You know more than you think you know, just as you know less
than you want to know.” Dorian Gray frowned and turned his
head away. He could not help liking the tall, graceful young man who was standing
by him. His romantic Olive colored face and worn expression interested him. There
was something in his low languid voice that was absolutely
fascinating. His cool, white, flowerlike hands, even, had a curious charm. They
moved, as he spoke, like music, and seemed to have a language of their own. But he
felt afraid of him, and ashamed of being afraid. Why had it been left for a
stranger to reveal him to himself? He had known Basil hallwood for months, but the
friendship between them had never altered him. Suddenly there had come
someone across his life who seemed to have disclosed to him life’s mystery. And,
yet, what was there to be afraid of? He
was not a school boy or a girl. It was absurd to be
frightened. “Let us go and sit in the shade,” said Lord Henry. “Parker has brought
out the drinks, and if you stay any longer in this glare, you will be quite
spoiled, and Basil will never paint you again. You really must not allow yourself
to become sunburnt. It would be unbecoming.” “What can it matter?” cried
Dorian Gray, laughing, as he sat down on the seat at the end of the garden. “It
should matter everything to you, Mr. Gray.” “Why?” “Because you have the most marvelous
youth, and youth is the one thing worth having.” “I don’t feel that, Lord
Henry.” “No, you don’t feel it now someday when you are old and
wrinkled and ugly, when thought has seared your forehead with its lines, and
passion branded your lips with its hideous fires, you will feel it, you will
feel it terribly. Now, wherever you go, you charm the world. Will it always be
so? You have a wonderfully beautiful face, Mr. Gray. Don’t frown. You have. And beauty
is a form of genius— —is higher, indeed, than genius, as it needs no
explanation. It is of the great facts of the world, like sunlight, or Springtime or
the reflection in dark waters of that silver shell we call the moon. It cannot
be questioned. It has its divine right of sovereignty. It makes princes of those
who have it. You smile? Ah! when you have lost it you won’t
smile.... People say sometimes that beauty is only superficial. That may be so, but
at least it is not so superficial as thought is. To me, beauty is the wonder of
wonders. It is only shallow people who do not judge by appearances. The true mystery of the
world is the visible, not the invisible.... Yes, Mr. Gray, the gods have been
good to you. But what the gods give they quickly take away. You have only a few
years in which to live really, perfectly, and fully. When your youth goes, your beauty
will go with it, and then you will suddenly discover that there are no
triumphs left for you, or have to content yourself with those mean triumphs that
the memory of your past will make more bitter than defeats. Every month as it
wanes brings you nearer to something dreadful. Time is jealous of you, and wars
against your lies and your roses. You will become sow and Hollow cheed and dull
eyed You will suffer horribly.... Ah! realize your youth while you
have it. Don’t squander the gold of your days, listening to the tedious, trying to
improve the hopeless failure, or giving away your life to the ignorant, the common, and the
vulgar. These are the sickly aims, the false ideals, of our age. Live! Live the
wonderful life that is in you! Let nothing be lost upon you. Be always
searching for new sensations. Be afraid of nothing.... A new Hedonism— —that is what
our centry wants. You might be its visible symbol. With your personality
there is nothing you could not do. The world belongs to you for a season.... The
moment I met you I saw that you were quite unconscious of what you really are,
of what you really might be. There was so much in you that charmed
me that I felt I must tell you something about yourself. I thought how tragic it
would be if you were wasted. For there is such a little time that your youth will
last— —such a little time. The common Hill Flowers wither, but they blossom again.
The burnam will be as yellow next June as it is now. In a month there will be
purple stars on the clematis, and year after year the green night of its leaves
will hold its purple stars. But we never get back our youth.
The pulse of joy that beats in us at 20 becomes sluggish. Our limbs fail, our
senses rot. We degenerate into hideous puppets, haunted by the memory of the
passions of which we were too much afraid, and the exquisite temptations
that we had not the courage to yield to.
Youth! Youth! There is absolutely nothing in the world but
youth!” Dorian Gray listened open eyed and wondering. The spray of lilac fell from
his hand upon the gravel. A furry bee came and buzzed around it for a moment.
Then it began to scramble all over the oval stellated globe of the tiny
blossoms. He watched it with that strange interest in trivial things that we try
try to develop when things of high import make us afraid, or when we are
stirred by some new emotion for which we cannot find expression, or when some
thought that terrifies us lays sudden siege to the brain and calls on us to
yield. After a time the bee flew away. He saw it creeping into the stained trumpet
of a Tyrion convolvulus. The flower seemed to quiver, and then swayed gently to and fro.
Suddenly the painter appeared St at the door of the studio and made stakato
signs for them to come in. They turned to each other and
smiled. “I am waiting,” he cried. “Do come in.
The light is quite perfect, and you can bring your drinks.” They rose up and sauntered down
the walk together. Two green and white butterflies fluttered past them, and in
the pear tree at the corner of the garden a thrush began to
sing. “You are glad you have met me, Mr.
Gray,” said Lord Henry, looking at him. “Yes I'm glad now. I wonder shall I always be
glad?” “Always that's a dreadful word. It makes me shudder when I hear it. Women
are so fond of using it. They spoil every romance by trying to make it last
forever It is a meaningless word, too. The only difference between a
caprice and a lifelong passion is that the caprice lasts a little
longer.” As they entered the studio, Dorian Gray put his hand upon Lord henryk's arm.
“In that case, let our friendship be a caprice,” he murmured, flushing at his own
boldness, then stepped up on the platform and resumed his pose. Lord Henry flung himself into a
large wicker armchair and watched him.
The sweep and dash of the brush on the canvas made the only sound that broke
the stillness, except when, now and then hallwood stepped back to look at his
work from a distance.
In the slanting beams that streamed through the open doorway the dust danced
and was golden. The heavy scent of the roses seemed to brood over
everything. After about a quarter of an hour hallwood stopped painting, looked
for a long time at Dorian Gray, and then for a long time at the picture, biting
the end of one of his huge brushes and frowning. “It is quite finished,” he cried
at last, and stooping down he wrote his name in long vermilion letters on the
leftand corner of the canvas. Lord Henry came over and examined
the picture. It was certainly a wonderful work of art, and a wonderful likeness as
well. “My dear fellow, I congratulate you most warmly,” he said. “It is the finest
portrait of modern times. Mr. Gray, come over and look at
yourself.” The lad started, as if awakened from some dream. “Is it really finished?” he
murmured, stepping down from the platform. “Quite finished,” said the painter. “And you have
sat splendidly today I'm awfully obliged to you.” “That is entirely due to me,” broke
in Lord Henry. “Isn’t it, Mr.
Gray?” Dorian made no answer, but passed listlessly in front of his picture and
turned towards it. When he saw it he drew back, and his cheeks flushed for a moment
with pleasure. A look of joy came into his eyes, as if he had recognized himself for the
first time. He stood there motionless and in wonder, dimly conscious that holwood
was speaking to him, but not catching the meaning of his
words. The sense of his own beauty came on him like a revelation. He had never
felt it before. Basil Hood's compliments had seemed to him to be merely the
charming exaggeration of friendship. He had listened to them, laughed at them,
forgotten them. They had not influenced his nature. Then had come Lord Henry
Waton with his strange panag on youth, his terrible warning of its brevity. That
had stirred him at the time, and now, as he stood gazing at the shadow of his own
loveliness, the full reality of the description flashed across
him. Yes, there would be a day when his face would be wrinkled and wizen, his
eyes dim and colorless the grace of his figure broken and deformed. The scarlet would pass away
from his lips and the gold steal from his hair. The life that was to make his soul
would mar his body. He would become dreadful, hideous, and
UNC As he thought of it, a sharp pang of pain struck through him like a knife and
made each delicate fiber of his nature quiver. His eyes deepened into amethyst,
and across them came a mist of tears. He
felt as if a hand of ice had been laid
upon his heart. “Don’t you like it?” cried hallwood at last, stung a little by the
lad’s silence, not understanding what it meant. “Of course he likes it,” said Lord
Henry. “Who wouldn’t like it? It is one of the greatest things in modern art. I will
give you anything you like to ask for it.
I must have it.” “It is not my property, Harry.” “Whose property is it Dorian of
course,” answered the painter. “He is a very lucky fellow.” “How sad it is!” murmured Dorian
Gray with his eyes still fixed upon his own portrait. “How sad it is! I shall grow
old, and horrible, and dreadful. But this picture will remain always young. It will
never be older than this particular day of June.... If it were only the other way! If
it were I who was to be always young, and the picture that was to grow old! For
that— —for that— —I would give everything! Yes, there is there is nothing
in the whole world I would not give! I would give my soul for
that!” “You would hardly care for such an arrangement, Basil,” cried Lord Henry,
laughing. “It would be rather hard lines on your work.” “I should object very
strongly, Harry,” said holwood Dorian Gray turned and looked at
him. “I believe you would, Basil. You like your art better than your friends. I am
no more to you than a green bronze figure. Hardly as much, I dare say.”
The painter stared in amazement. It was so unlike Dorian to
speak like that. What had happened? He seemed quite angry. His face was flushed and his cheeks
burning. “Yes,” he continued, “I am less to you than your ivory Hermes or your
silver fa You will like them always. How long will you like me? Till I have my
first wrinkle, I suppose. I know, now, that when one loses one’s good looks, whatever
they may be, one loses everything. Your picture has taught me that. Lord Henry
Waton is perfectly right. Youth is the only thing worth having. When I find that
I'm growing old, I shall kill myself hwood turned pale and caught his
hand. “Dorian! Dorian!” he cried, “don’t talk like that I've never had such a friend
as you, and I shall never have such another. You are not jealous of material
things, are you?— ?—you who are finer than any of them!”
“I am jealous of everything whose beauty does not die. I am jealous of the
portrait you have painted of me. Why should it keep what I must
lose? Every moment that passes takes something from me and gives something to
it. Oh, if it were only the other way! If the picture could change, and I could be
always what I am now! Why did you paint it? It will mock me someday mock me
horribly!” The hot tears welled into his eyes; he tore his hand away and, flinging
himself on the divan, he buried his face in the cushions, as though he was praying.
“This is your doing, Harry,” said the painter bitterly. Lord Henry shrugged his
shoulders. “It is the real Dorian Gray— —that is all.” “It is not.” “If it is not, what
have I to do with it?” “You should have gone away when I asked you,” he muttered. “I
stayed when you asked me,” was Lord henryk's answer.
“Harry, I can’t quarrel with my two best friends at once, but between you both you
have made me hate the finest piece of work I have ever done, and I will destroy
it. What is it but canvas and color I will not let it come across our three
lives and mar them.” Dorian Gray lifted his golden head from the pillow, and with
palid face and tear stained eyes, looked at him as he walked over to the deal
Painting table that was set beneath the high curtained window
window. What was he doing there? His fingers were straying about among the
litter of tin tubes and dry brushes, seeking for something. Yes, it was for the
long pallet knife with its thin blade of lithe steel. He had found it at last. He
was going to rip up the canvas. With a stifled sob the lad leaped from the
couch, and, rushing over to hallwood tore the knife out of his hand, and flung it
to the end of the studio. “Don’t don't Basil, don’t!” he cried. “It would be
murder!” “I glad you appreciate my work at last, Dorian,” said the painter coldly when
he had recovered from his surprise. “I never thought you
would.” “Appreciate it? I am in love with it, Basil. It is part of myself. I feel
that.” “Well, as soon as you are dry, you shall be varnished, and framed, and sent
home. Then you can do what you like with yourself.” And he walked across the room and rang
the bell for tea. “You will have tea, of course, Dorian?
And so will you, Harry? Or do you object to such simple
pleasures?” “I adore simple pleasures,” said Lord Henry. “They are the last refuge of
the complex. But I don’t like scenes, except on the stage. What absurd fellows
you are, both of you! I wonder who it was defined man as a rational animal. It was
the most premature a definition ever given. Man is many things, but he is not
rational I'm glad he is not, after all— —though I wish you chaps would not
squabble over the picture. You had much better let me have it, Basil. This silly
boy doesn’t really want it, and I really do.” “If you let anyone have it but me,
Basil, I shall never forgive you!” cried Dorian Gray; “and I don’t allow people to
call me a silly boy.” “You know the picture is yours, Dorian.
I gave it to you before it existed.” “And you know you have been a little silly, Mr.
Gray, and that you don’t really object to being reminded that you are extremely
young.” “I should have objected very strongly this morning, Lord Henry this
morning! You have lived since then.” There came a knock at the door, and
the butler entered with a laden tea tray and set it down upon a small Japanese
table. There was a rattle of cups and saucers and the hissing of a flute
georgean n Two globe-shaped china dishes were brought in by a page. Dorian Gray
went over and poured out the tea. The two men sauntered languidly to the table and
examined what was under the covers. “Let us go to the theater tonight
said Lord Henry. “There is sure to be something on, somewhere. I have promised
to dine at whites but it is only with an
old friend, so I can send him a wire to
say that I am ill, or that I am prevented from coming in con consquence of a
subsequent engagement. I think that would be a rather nice excuse: it would have
all the surprise of cander It is such a bore putting on one’s dress clothes muttered hallwood
And, when one has them on, they are so horrid.” “Yes,” answered Lord Henry
dreamily, “the costume of the 19th century is detestable. It is so somber so depressing.
Sin is the only real color element left in modern life.”
“You really must not say things like that before Dorian, Harry.” “Before which Dorian?
The one who is pouring out tea for us, or the one in the picture?” “Before either.” “I
should like to come to the theater with you, Lord Henry,” said the lad. “Then you
shall come; and you will come, too, Basil, won’t you?” “I can’t, really. I would sooner
not. I have a lot of work to do.” “Well, then,
you and I will go alone, Mr. Gray.” “I should like that
awfully.” The painter bit his lip and walked over, cup in hand, to the picture. “I
shall stay with the real Dorian,” he said, sadly. “Is it the real Dorian?” cried the
original of the portrait, strolling across to him. “Am I really like that?” “Yes;
you are just like that.” “How wonderful, Basil!” “At least you are like it in
appearance. But it will never alter sigh hallwood That is
something.” “What a fuss people make about fidelity!” exclaimed Lord Henry. “Why, even
in love it is purely a question for physiology. It has nothing to do with our
own will. Young men want to be faithful, and are not; old men want to be faithless,
and cannot: that is all one can say.” “Don’t go to the theater tonight Dorian,” said
holwood Stop and dine with me.” “I can’t, Basil.” “Why?”
“Because I have promised Lord Henry Waton to go with him.” “He won’t like you the
better for keeping your promises. He always breaks his own. I beg you not to
go.” Dorian Gray laughed and shook his head. “I intreat you.” The lad hesitated, and
looked over at Lord Henry, who was watching them from the tea table with an amused
smile. “I must go, Basil,” he answered. “Very well,” said holwood and he
went over and laid down his cup on the tray. “It is rather late, and, as you have
to dress, you had better lose no time goodbye Harry goodbye Dorian. Come and see me soon. Come
tomorrow Certainly.” “You won’t forget?” “No, of course not,” cried Dorian. “And Harry!” “Yes,
Basil?” “Remember what I asked you, when we were in the garden this morning.” “I I have
forgotten it.” “I trust you.” “I wish I could trust myself,” said Lord Henry, laughing.
“Come, Mr. Gray, my handsome is outside, and I can drop you at your own place goodbye
Basil. It has been a most interesting afternoon.” As the door closed behind them,
the painter flung himself down on a sofa, and a look of pain came into his face. CHAPTER